Let's talk about one of those small words that does a ton of heavy lifting in the English
英語の小さな単語ながら、
language.
非常に重要な働きをする言葉について話しましょう。
It's a word you probably use, I don't know, dozens of times a day without even thinking
皆さんも日に何十回と
about it.
無意識に使っているであろう言葉です。
But what if I told you that really mastering this one simple word could make your speaking
このシンプルな単語をマスターすれば、
and writing so much clearer, so much more sophisticated?
会話や文章がより明確で洗練されたものになります。
Well today, we're going to unlock the power of when.
今日は "when" の持つ力について解き明かしていきます。
So to really see the power of when in action, let's start with a really simple problem.
"when" の力を実感するために、簡単な問題から始めましょう。
Just imagine we have two separate moments in time, two different ideas that we want
例えば、2つの異なる時間、2つの異なる出来事を
to connect.
つなぎ合わせたいとします。
Okay, here's our first moment.
まず一つ目の文です。
A simple, complete idea, right?
これだけで完結していますね。
I was watching television.
「私はテレビを見ていました」。
This sentence, it stands perfectly fine all on its own.
この文は、それだけで完全に意味が成り立ちます。
It tells us exactly what was going on.
何が起きていたかを正確に伝えています。
And then, boom, here's our second moment, also a totally complete idea.
そして、二つ目の文です。これもまた、完結した文。
He came.
「彼が来た」。
An action happened.
一つの行動が起きました。
But right now, these are just two separate facts.
しかし今のままでは、二つの別々の事実でしかありません。
One thing happened, and then another thing happened.
ある事が起こり、そして別の事が起こった。
They're not really connected.
これでは、二つの出来事に関連性がありません。
So this is the big question for today.
さて、ここからが本題です。
How can we link these two separate events together into one single flowing thought?
この二つの出来事を、一つの滑らかな文にまとめるにはどうすれば良いでしょう？
How do we show that they're actually related in time?
時間的な関係性を示すには、どうしたら良いでしょうか？
Now our first instinct, you know, might be to just grab a simple word to show that these
まず思いつくのは、二つの出来事がほぼ同時に起きたことを示す
two things happen around the same time.
簡単な単語を使うことかもしれません。
Let's see what that looks like.
例えば、こんな風にです。
We could say, I was watching television then.
「私はテレビを見ていました。その時…」
Or maybe something like, I was watching television at that time.
あるいは、「私はその時、テレビを見ていました」でも良いでしょう。
And you know what?
分かりますよね？
This works.
これでも、言いたいことは十分に伝わります。
But it feels a little clunky, doesn't it?
しかし、少しぎこちない感じがしませんか？
The ideas still kind of feel like two separate sentences that we just shoved next to each
二つの文を、無理やり
other.
くっつけたようです。
We can do better.
もっと良い方法があります。
And this, my friends, brings us to our hero word for the day.
そこで登場するのが、本日の主役となる単語です。
This is the elegant solution that can seamlessly merge these two ideas into one fluid, really
二つの文を、一つの流れるような洗練された文に、
sophisticated sentence.
滑らかに繋げてくれるのがこの単語です。
Let's bring in when.
"when"を使ってみましょう。
Ah, just look at that.
ほら、見てください。
I was watching television when he came.
「私は彼が来たとき、テレビを見ていました」
See how that just flows?
どうです、とても滑らかでしょう？
It's not two separate events anymore.
もはや二つの別々の出来事ではなく、
It's one single story.
一つの物語になりました。
That little word, when, acts like the perfect glue, binding these two moments together.
この "when" という小さな単語が、二つの瞬間を繋ぎ合わせる、完璧な接着剤の役割を果たしているのです。
So what's the magic trick here?
では、どういう仕組みなのでしょうか？
Well, that little phrase, when he came, it acts as a single unit.
"when he came" というフレーズは、それ全体で一つの塊として機能します。
It's basically a package deal.
ひとつのパッケージのようなものです。
When grabs a subject, in this case, he, and a verb, came, and turns the whole thing into
"when" は、"he" という主語と "came" という動詞をとり、
a super precise description of a moment in time.
それ全体で「ある特定の時点」を正確に表現するのです。
It literally means, at the time that he came.
文字通り、「彼が来たその時に」という意味になります。
Okay, so now that we know what when is doing, let's talk about a pro tip for how to use
"when" の働きが分かったところで、
it.
その使い方に関する上級テクニックです。
When isn't just powerful, it's also really flexible.
"when" は強力なだけでなく、非常に柔軟です。
You've got options.
いくつか選択肢があります。
Now what's really cool is that you have two perfectly correct ways to build this sentence.
素晴らしいことに、この文には二通りの正しい作り方があります。
You can stick the when part at the end, like I was sleeping when he came.
一つは "when" の部分を文末に置く形です。「I was sleeping when he came.」
Or if you want to switch things up, you can lead with it.
あるいは、順番を変えて文頭に持ってくることもできます。
When he came, I was sleeping.
「When he came, I was sleeping.」
Both are 100% correct, and they mean the exact same thing.
どちらも100%正しく、意味も全く同じです。
But, and this is a big but, there is one critical rule you absolutely cannot forget.
しかし、絶対に忘れてはならない、重要なルールが一つだけあります。
If you choose to put that when clause at the very beginning of your sentence, you
もし "when の S + V" を文頭に持ってくる場合は、
must, must, must separate it from the main idea with a comma.
必ずコンマ（,）で区切らなければなりません。
That tiny little comma is doing some serious work there to keep your sentence clear and
この小さなコンマが、文を明確で読みやすくするために、
easy to read.
非常に重要な役割を担っているのです。
Don't forget it.
忘れないでくださいね。
Alright, time to put this into practice.
では、練習してみましょう。
Here's a quick challenge for you.
簡単な問題を出します。
Unscramble the words you see in the parentheses to finish the sentence.
カッコ内の単語を並べ替えて、文を完成させてください。
Go on, I'll give you a second to think about it.
少し考える時間をあげます。
And there you have it.
はい、できましたね。
My mother was a good tennis player when she was young.
「私の母は若い頃、テニスが上手でした。」
That when clause just neatly connects her tennis skill to a specific time in her life.
この "when" が、彼女のテニスの腕前と、若い頃という特定の時期を、見事に結びつけています。
Perfect, you got it.
完璧です。
So now it's time to pull back the curtain a little bit and reveal what's really going
さて、ここからは文法的な観点から、
on here from a grammar perspective.
この "when" の正体を明らかにしていきましょう。
What is the true identity of this super flexible, super useful word?
この非常に柔軟で便利な単語の
Let's ask the big question.
正体は何なのでしょうか？
We know it connects ideas, sure, but what do we actually call a word that does that?
文法の世界では、このような働きをする単語を
What's its official job title in the world of grammar?
何と呼ぶのでしょう？
The real key here is that when isn't just connecting random words, it's connecting
重要なのは、"when" は単語と単語ではなく、
two complete ideas, or what we call clauses.
二つの完結した文、つまり S + V を結びつけているという点です。
We have, I was watching television, that's a subject and a verb.
「私はテレビを見ていた」には主語と動詞があり、
And we have, he came, that's another subject and another verb.
「彼が来た」にも主語と動詞があります。
When is the bridge that connects them.
"when" は、これら二つを繋ぐ架け橋です。
And any word that does this job has a special name, it's a conjunction.
そして、この役割を果たす単語には「接続詞」という特別な名前があります。
So that's the secret identity.
これが "when" の正体です。
In this sentence, when is acting as a conjunction, joining two complete thoughts.
この文の中で "when" は、二つの完結した文を繋ぐ「接続詞」として機能しているのです。
You already know other conjunctions like and, but, and so.
皆さんは既に、"and" や "but"、"so" といった接続詞を知っていますね。
Well, when is just another powerful member of that same family.
"when" も、その仲間の一つなのです。
So let's just do a quick recap of our journey, right?
ここまでの内容を振り返ってみましょう。
We started with a simple adverb, then, which felt a little… disconnected.
最初は "then" という副詞を使いましたが、少し不自然でした。
Then we upgraded to using when as a conjunction to create a single flowing sentence.
次に "when" を接続詞として使い、一つの滑らかな文を作りました。
And finally, we mastered its flexibility, learning we can even move it to the front
そして、文頭に置くこともできるという柔軟性も学びました。
of the sentence as long as we use that comma.
その際はコンマが必要でしたね。
Pretty cool how we went from a simple word to a powerful grammatical tool.
一つの単語が、いかに強力な文法ツールになるかが分かりました。
So I'll leave you with a little something to think about.
最後に、少し考えてみてください。
In the sentence, I was sleeping when he came, which part feels like the main event?
「I was sleeping when he came.」という文では、どちらが主となる出来事だと感じますか？
The sleeping?
寝ていたことでしょうか？
Or his arrival?
それとも、彼が来たことでしょうか？
And what about if you flip it?
では、順番を入れ替えたらどうでしょう？
When he came, I was sleeping.
「When he came, I was sleeping.」
Does that change which part feels more important?
これだと、どちらがより重要だと感じますか？
That's the subtle power these little words have.
こうした小さな言葉には、このような繊細な力があるのです。
Keep exploring.
これからも探求を続けてください。